Guide to the Gertrude Duby Blom exhibit photographs, 1940s-2004 and undated RL.10084
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Gertrude Duby Blom exhibit photographs
1941-2004 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Blom, Gertrude Duby
Blom, Gertrude Duby -- Gertrude Blom: bearing witness
RL.10084
9 Linear Feet Approx. 420 items
Gertrude Duby Blom (1901-1993) was a Swiss-born journalist, anthropologist, and environmental activist who documented the cultures of indigenous Mayan people in the jungle highlands of Chiapas, Mexico. Collection comprises 71 black-and-white exhibit prints featuring images taken by Gertrude Duby Blom between 1941 and 1979 in the highland jungles and towns of the state of Chiapas, Mexico. The photographs were printed in 1982 by Barry Norris, Blom's close friend and collaborator, for a traveling exhibition that opened in 1984 in New York City. The landscapes and portraits depict the cultural and ecological environments inhabited by individuals and groups of indigenous Maya, predominantly the Lacandon; there are also images of Latino immigrants to the region, chiefly lumber industry workers and their families, and other townspeople in San Cristobal. Scenes from camps and towns portray mealtimes, hunting and gathering expeditions, agricultural customs, religious ceremonies, folk Catholicism and its rituals, classrooms, medical clinics, and street scenes. Later images attest to the destruction of native ecosystems and the rapidly changing culture of the indigenous peoples. The matted gelatin silver prints vary in size from 11x14 to 22x22 inches; there is also one 26x26 inch matted print. Accompanying the photographs are project correspondence, notes, publicity, and other materials (1983-20043) documenting the collaboration between Alex Harris, documentary photographer from the Center for Documentary Studies at Duke University, and individuals in Mexico and the U.S., which resulted in a major exhibit, "People of the forest: photographs of the Maya by Getrude Blom," launched in 1984, and the publication of "Gertrude Blom: bearing witness" (1984). Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
Biographical Note
Gertrude Duby Blom (1901-1993) was a journalist, anthropologist, and activist of Swiss descent who spent more than 40 years documenting the Mayan cultures of Chiapas, Mexico. She married Kurt Duby in 1925; they divorced several years later. Forced to emigrate from her native country in 1930s because of her Socialist and anti-Fascist activities, she traveled to England, then made her way to Mexico City, where she began a long association with the Mexican people and their country.
A major turn in life occurred when Blom met with anthropologists who were studying the native peoples of central Mexico's highlands and jungles; on one of her first trips she encountered the Lacandon tribe of Mayan Indians, who had only just been in contact with Europeans since the late 1880s. In 1943, anthropologist Frans Blom invited her to join an expedition to the cloud forests of Chiapas, thus beginning a lifelong alliance. The Bloms, who married in 1951, focused all of their research, support, and patrimony on this area of Chiapas and on the Lancandon in particular, studying and documenting the plight of indigenous peoples from the 1940s to the 1980s as settlers deforested their territory and brought their way of life to an end.
In the 1950s, Gertrude and Frans established Casa Na Bolom (House of the Jaguar), a research center and hostel, which also served as a center for a support network for the Lacandon and other indigenous peoples. By the 1970s the Bloms has also shaped it into an active center for environmental activism in support of the jungles of Chiapas, threatened by mining, logging, and modern methods of farming.
Blom published her first collection of photographs in 1984, Gertrude Blom - bearing witness, sponsored by the Center for Documentary Studies (CDS) at Duke University and guided to publication by Alex Harris and Margaret Sartor of the CDS. A major exhibit of Blom's images opened in New York City in 1984, titled People of the Forest: photographs of the Maya by Gertrude Blom, and traveled subsequently to major cities in the U.S. and overseas through the 2000s.
Gertrude Duby Blom passed away December 23, 1993, and is buried in La Selva Lacandona alongside her husband, Frans Blom.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Arrangement
Collection is arranged in two series, Exhibit Prints and Exhibit Project Records. The matted prints are arranged by size and chronologically within size groups.
Collection Overview
Collection comprises 71 black-and-white exhibit prints featuring images taken by anthropologist, activist, and journalist Gertrude Duby Blom between 1941 and 1979 in the highland jungles and towns of the state of Chiapas, Mexico. The photographs were printed in 1982 by Barry Norris, Blom's close friend and collaborator, for a major exhibition of her work that opened in 1984 in New York City.
The landscapes and portraits taken by Blom depict the cultural and ecological environments inhabited by indigenous Maya, predominantly the Lacandon, but also neighboring Tzotzil and Tzeltal; there are also images of Latino immigrants to the region, chiefly lumber industry workers and their families, and other townspeople in San Cristobal. Scenes from camps and towns portray mealtimes, hunting and gathering expeditions, agricultural customs, religious ceremonies, folk Catholicism and its rituals, classrooms, medical clinics, and street scenes. Later images attest to the destruction of native ecosystems and the rapidly changing culture of the indigenous peoples. The matted gelatin silver prints vary in size from 11x14 to 22x22 inches; there is also one 26x26 inch matted print.
Accompanying the photographs are files of project correspondence, notes, publicity, and other materials (1983-2004) documenting the collaboration between Alex Harris, documentary photographer of the Center for Documentary Studies at Duke University, and individuals in Mexico and the U.S., which resulted in a major international traveling exhibit, "People of the forest: photographs of the Maya by Getrude Blom," launched in 1984, and the publication of a book of essays and images, "Gertrude Blom: bearing witness" (1984), edited by Alex Harris and Margaret Sartor.
Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
Provenance
The Gertrude Duby Blom exhibit photographs were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a transfer from the Center for Documentary Studies in 2013.
Anthropology, Cultural -- Chiapas Highlands (Mexico); Chiapas Highlands (Mexico) -- Pictorial works.; Chiapas Highlands (Mexico) -- Exhibits.; Gelatin silver prints; Mayas -- Pictorial works.; Photographers -- Mexico; Photographs; Photographers -- United States -- Correspondence; Indians of Mexico -- Cultural assimilation.; Deforestation -- Mexico -- Pictorial works.; Documentary Photography -- Mexico; Lacandona Forest (Mexico) -- Pictorial works.; Mexico -- Social conditions -- 20th century.; Indians of Mexico -- Social conditions.; Lacandon Indians -- Pictorial works.; Norris, Barry; Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University); Duke University. Center for Documentary Studies
- Exhibit Prints, 1941-1982; 7 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  Series of 71 exhibit prints of black-and-white images taken by Gertrude Duby Blom between 1941 and 1982 in the highland jungles and towns of Chiapas, Mexico. The photographs were printed in 1982 by Barry Norris, Blom's close friend and collaborator since 1977. The matted prints are arranged in groups by size, from 11x14 to 22x22 inches (mat sizes), accompanied by a larger matted print measuring 26x26 inches. Within size groups, prints are arranged by year. Captions are taken from original text printed on the mats beneath each image.
  - Pepe Castillo, Lacandon, Monte Libano, 1943; 11 x 14 inches (Box 1, Image RL_10084_P_001)
  - Vicente Bor performing religious ceremony with corn gruel, Lacandon, Jataté River, 1950; 11 x 14 inches (Box 1, Image RL_10084_P_002)
  - K'in García in dugout canoe, Lacandon, Najá, 1958; 11 x 14 inches (Box 1, Image RL_10084_P_003)
  - Zapatista, Yautepec, 1941; 14 x 17 inches (Box 2, Image RL_10084_P_004)
  - Ladino women, Malinalco, 1944; 14 x 17 inches (Box 2, Image RL_10084_P_005)
  - Lacandon man, Najá, 1948; 14 x 17 inches (Box 2, Image RL_10084_P_006)
  - Don Florentino with his son, Tzeltal, Jetjá, 1943; 15 x 15 inches (Box 3, Image RL_10084_P_007)
  - Manuel Castellanos, Tzotzil, assisting voter registration of Chamula Indians, 1946; 15 x 15 inches (Box 3, Image RL_10084_P_008)
  - Pedro Contreras with armadillo, San Quintín, 1946; 15 x 15 inches (Box 3, Image RL_10084_P_009)
  - Mahogany loggers at the Lacanjá River, Montería, 1948; 15 x 15 inches (Box 3, Image RL_10084_P_010)
  - Vicente Chaqueta with his son, Lacandon, Censo, 1948; 15 x 15 inches (Box 3, Image RL_10084_P_011)
  - Calle Diego Dugelay, San Cristóbal de las Casas, 1951; 15 x 15 inches (Box 3, Image RL_10084_P_012)
  - Chan K'in Viejo weighing tobacco, Lacandon, Najá, 1952; 15 x 15 inches (Box 3, Image RL_10084_P_013)
  - Medical clinic of the National Indian Institute, Chamula, 1952; 15 x 15 inches (Box 3, Image RL_10084_P_014)
  - Vicente Bor, with sons K'in and K'ayum, leaving the jungle for Na Bolom, Lacandon, El Real, 1952; 15 x 15 inches (Box 3, Image RL_10084_P_015)
  - Zinacantec nurse in the National Indian Institute, Tzotzil, Zinacantán, 1952; 15 x 15 inches (Box 3, Image RL_10084_P_016)
  - Chenalhó religious official in the market, Tzotzil, Chalchihuitán, 1954; 15 x 15 inches (Box 3, Image RL_10084_P_017)
  - Lacandon jungle between Las Margaritas and San Quintín, Tojolobal Indians, 1955; 15 x 15 inches (Box 3, Image RL_10084_P_018)
  - Ladino man on horseback, Santiago, 1955; 15 x 15 inches (Box 3, Image RL_10084_P_019)
  - Festival of San Sebastián, Tzotzil, San Bartolomé de los Llanos, 1955; 15 x 15 inches (Box 3, Image RL_10084_P_020)
  - Preparation for the Festival of San Andrés: sacristans building the sacred path, Tzotzil, San Andrés, 1956; 15 x 15 inches (Box 3, Image RL_10084_P_021)
  - Tzotzil actors during the Festival of San Sebastián, Zincantán, 1958; 15 x 15 inches (Box 4, Image RL_10084_P_022)
  - Vincente Bor performing god house ceremony, Lacandon, Jataté, 1958; 15 x 15 inches (Box 4, Image RL_10084_P_023)
  - Zinacantec musicians, Tzotzil, Navenchauc, 1958; 15 x 15 inches (Box 4, Image RL_10084_P_024)
  - Zinatec boys at political rally for López Mateos, Tzotzil, San Cristóbal de las Casas, 1958; 15 x 15 inches (Box 4, Image RL_10084_P_025)
  - Chamula women, Tzotzil, Romerillo, 1959; 15 x 15 inches (Box 4, Image RL_10084_P_026)
  - Lacandon boy, Cedro, 1959; 15 x 15 inches (Box 4, Image RL_10084_P_027)
  - Lacandones from Monte Libano, El Real, 1959; 15 x 15 inches (Box 4, Image RL_10084_P_028)
  - Chilón, 1960; 15 x 15 inches (Box 4, Image RL_10084_P_029)
  - Masked dancer, Tzotzil, Chenalhó Carnival, 1960; 15 x 15 inches (Box 4, Image RL_10084_P_030)
  - The Fire Run, Tzotzil, San Juan Chamula Carnival, 1960; 15 x 15 inches (Box 4, Image RL_10084_P_031)
  - Tzeltal woman in the market, Yajalón, 1961; 15 x 15 inches (Box 4, Image RL_10084_P_032)
  - Chan K'in Viejo with his son, K'in García, in the god house, Lacandon, Najá, 1963; 15 x 15 inches (Box 4, Image RL_10084_P_033)
  - Celestino, Lacandon, Lacanjá Chan Sayab, 1964; 15 x 15 inches (Box 4, Image RL_10084_P_034)
  - Old Tzotzil man, San Andrés, 1965; 15 x 15 inches (Box 4, Image RL_10084_P_035)
  - Tzotzil cutting hair, Chilil, 1965; 15 x 15 inches (Box 4, Image RL_10084_P_036)
  - San Andrés Indians visiting Santiago, Tzotzil, Santiago, 1967; 15 x 15 inches (Box 5, Image RL_10084_P_037)
  - Magdalenas dressing the saint for a visit to Santa Marta, Tzotzil, 1968; 15 x 15 inches (Box 5, Image RL_10084_P_038)
  - Ladino students reenacting Aztec history, San Miguel Mitontic, 1969; 15 x 15 inches (Box 5, Image RL_10084_P_039)
  - Chamula family on the road to Tzmtehaitz, Tzotzil, The Sacred Mountain of Chamula, 1971; 15 x 15 inches (Box 5, Image RL_10084_P_040)
  - Tzotzil captains and patron in festival procession, Santiago, 1971; 15 x 15 inches (Box 5, Image RL_10084_P_041)
  - K'ayum and Pedro K'ayum, Lacandon, Lacanjá Chan Sayab, 1972; 15 x 15 inches (Box 5, Image RL_10084_P_042)
  - Tzotzil men in front of the church, Santiago, 1974; 15 x 15 inches (Box 5, Image RL_10084_P_043)
  - Chan K'in Viejo with his wife Koh, Lacandon, Trudi's camp at Najá, 1976; 15 x 15 inches (Box 5, Image RL_10084_P_044)
  - Chan K'in Presidente, Mateo Viejo, and K'in Garcia in the highlands, Lacandon, 1977; 15 x 15 inches (Box 5, Image RL_10084_P_045)
  - K'ayum Ma'ax, Lacandon, Najá, 1977; 15 x 15 inches (Box 5, Image RL_10084_P_046)
  - Lacandon women making clay figures to sell, Najá, 1978; 15 x 15 inches (Box 5, Image RL_10084_P_047)
  - K'ayum Ma'ax with accordion, Lacandon, Najá, 1979; 15 x 15 inches (Box 5, Image RL_10084_P_048)
  - Chamula boy carrying burlap bag of pine boughs for a ceremony, Tzotztil, undated, 15 x 15 inches (Box 5, Image RL_10084_P_049)
  - Clearing land, Frontera Corozal, 15 x 15 inches (Box 5, Image RL_10084_P_050)
  - Lacandon men near the Chocoljá River, Arena, 1948; 22 x 22 inches (Box 6, Image RL_10084_P_051)
  - Old Tzotzil man carrying wheat, Huistán, 1952; 22 x 22 inches (Box 6, Image RL_10084_P_052)
  - Chamula teacher with Zinacantec students, Tzotzil, Ichin Ton, 1953; 22 x 22 inches (Box 6, Image RL_10084_P_053)
  - Father Bermudez with festival officials, Tzotzil, San Juan Chamula Carnival, 1955; 22 x 22 inches (Box 6, Image RL_10084_P_054)
  - Zinacantec musicians, Tzotzil, Festival of San Sebastián, San Bartolomé de los Llanos, 1955; 22 x 22 inches (Box 6, Image RL_10084_P_055)
  - Pedro K'ayum cutting down ceiba tree with machete, Lacandon, Jataté, 1958; 22 x 22 inches (Box 6, Image RL_10084_P_056)
  - Religious procession in the barrio of San Felipe, San Cristóbal de las Casas, 1958; 22 x 22 inches (Box 6, Image RL_10084_P_057)
  - Kimbor, Lacandon, Najá, 1959; 22 x 22 inches (Box 6, Image RL_10084_P_058)
  - K'in Obregon, Lacandon, ruins of Lacanjá, 1961; 22 x 22 inches (Box 6, Image RL_10084_P_059)
  - The Saint, San Andrés, visiting at the Festival of Santiago, Tzotzil, Santiago, 1962; 22 x 22 inches (Box 6, Image RL_10084_P_060)
  - Chamula woman and child at Mitontic Festival, Tzotzil, San Miguel, 1963; 22 x 22 inches (Box 7, Image RL_10084_P_061)
  - Ceiba, The Sacred Tree of the Maya, Yaxchilán, 1967; 22 x 22 inches (Box 7, Image RL_10084_P_062)
  - Religious procession, Tzotzil, San Miguel Mitontic, 1967; 22 x 22 inches (Box 7, Image RL_10084_P_063)
  - Cut mahogany, Lacandon jungle near Lacanjá Chan Sayab, 1968; 22 x 22 inches (Box 7, Image RL_10084_P_064)
  - Gourd tree, Huitiupán, 1972; 22 x 22 inches (Box 7, Image RL_10084_P_065)
  - Chamula woman praying to San Miguel, Tzotzil, San Miguel Mitontic, 1973; 22 x 22 inches (Box 7, Image RL_10084_P_066)
  - Lacandon jungle between Sibál and Najá, 1974; 22 x 22 inches (Box 7, Image RL_10084_P_067)
  - Religious official, Tzotzil, Santiago, 1974; 22 x 22 inches (Box 7, Image RL_10084_P_068)
  - Lacanjá River, 1975; 22 x 22 inches (Box 7, Image RL_10084_P_069)
  - Cut mahogany, Najá, 1979; 22 x 22 inches (Box 7, Image RL_10084_P_070)
  - Deforested hillside, Lacandon jungle between El Real and Najá (oversize exhibit print), 1982; 26 x 26 inches; One oversize matted exhibit print (Oversize-folder 1)
- Exhibit Project Records, 1983-2004 and undated; 1 box
  Series is comprised of correspondence, notes, financial records, and travel schedules relating to the creation and curation of the exhibit, People of the Forest: Photographs of the Maya by Gertrude Blom, which opened at the International Center of Photography in New York City in April 1984. The documents are accompanied by a large publicity poster for the "People of the Forest" exhibit (1984), and two copies of the book, released the same year as the exhibit, Gertrude Blom: Bearing Witness. Series is arranged in chronological order; original folder titles have been retained.
  - "People of the Forest" exhibition, text and panels, 1983 November 22-1995 March 28 and undated (Box 8)
  - "People of the Forest" exhibition, correspondence, 1983 December 12-1998 April 16 (Box 8)
  - Na Bolom, correspondence and records, 1988 April-1998 March 3 (Box 8)
  - Environmental programming, 1997 September 3-1998 March 3 (Box 8)
  - Exhibit redesign by the Smithsonian, 1997 December 9-2003 July 7 and undated (Box 8)
  - Asheville (N.C.) exhibit, 1999, 1998 July 13-1999 November 17 and undated (Box 8)
  - Alex Finlayson, proposal for play about Blom, circa 1998 (Box 8)
  - "People of the Forest" exhibit poster, 1984; 16x24 inches (Box 7)
- Oral Histories, 3 Files WAV, MP3, and PKV file; 1.21 Gigabytes
  - Barry Norris interviewed by Alex Harris, 2015; 00:53:21 minutes
    Scope and Contents
    Oral history recording Alex Harris in conversation with Barry Norris, Gertrude Blom's printer, November 18, 2015. Norris and Harris discuss creating the book, Gertrude Blom: Bearing Witness, Blom's temperament and approach to photography, and Norris's thoughts on digital scanning. Synchronized description of the interview can be found here: Interview index.